Finding Aid to Roberta Cantow papers SSC.MS.00559
Sophia Smith Collection
Roberta Cantow papers
1965-2018
Sophia Smith Collection
Cantow, Roberta
SSC.MS.00559
14.75 linear feet (18 boxes)
525 Megabytes (archived website)
Roberta Cantow is a filmmaker. This collection of her papers includes biographical information, personal writings, artwork, photographs, awards, and psychic readings (audio tapes), photographs, correspondence, email, publicity, and other documents pertaining to the production and distribution of Cantow's films, as well as Cantow's thoughts on issues and circumstances covered in the films, including: the documentary Clotheslines, Dr. Clown (about Patch Adams, M.D.) The Book of Laughs, If This Ain't Heaven, and Illuminada.
Biographical / Historical
Filmmaker Roberta Cantow was born in Cleveland, Ohio to Janet Leah Wohfield and Lawrence Albert Cantow, M.D. She earned an A.B. from the University of Michigan in 1969, and an M.F.A. from the Tisch School of the Arts at New York University in 1972. From 1969 to 1970, she studied at the Etienne Decroux School of Mime in Paris, France. She is the founder of Buffalo Rose Productions (1982), Original Digital (1997), and One Of A Kind Video Portraits (1993-2003).
She has produced, directed and edited numerous independent films and videos, including The Book of Laughs (1988), If This Ain't Heaven (1984), Clotheslines (1981), Moon Festival (1994), Mosaics (1994), and Doctor Clown (1992).
Cantow often presents and discusses her work in public forums, and has served as an educator among multi-ethnic populations in community college, adult education, and youth-oriented museum and artist-in-residence programs. She has been the recipient of numerous grants, and has garnered many honors and awards for her work.
Scope and Contents
The Roberta Cantow Papers are comprised of biographical information, personal writings, artwork, photographs, awards, and psychic readings (audio tapes), photographs, correspondence, email, publicity, and other documents pertaining to the production and distribution of Cantow's films, as well as Cantow's thoughts on issues and circumstances covered in the films.
Audiovisual materials include original prints and copies in various formats (16mm film, video tape, DVDs, soundtrack, audio tapes, and audio CDs) of Cantow's films and performance pieces. The films are documentary and include Clotheslines, "an homage to women and their daily work,...a lively and humorous look at the relationship that women have with the chore of cleaning the family clothes.... In this documentary, layers of emotions come to the surface as the commonality of women's work is exposed." Other films include Dr. Clown, about Patch Adams, M.D.; The Book of Laughs, about the shared memories of two sisters; If This Ain't Heaven, the reminiscences of a fifty-year-old African American man; and Illuminada, a visual impression of Mexico. There are smaller amounts of materials pertaining to other films and film possibilities that Cantow pursued, e.g. a script for T The Revolt of the Mother, based on the novel by Mary E. Wilkins Freeman. There are also recorded interviews by Cantow of herbalist, Susan Weed, and Goddess scholar, Karen Tate.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for use without restriction beyond the standard terms and conditions of Smith College Special Collections, except for Cantow's diaries, which are closed to research until August 15, 2028.
Accruals
Periodic additions to collection are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Roberta Cantow began donating her papers to the Sophia Smith Collection in 2006.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
As a preservation measure, researchers must use digital copies of audiovisual materials in this collection. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request the creation of and access to digital copies. Some, but not all, of the audiovisual records have already had digital surrogates made.
This collection contains materials received from the donor in digital form that are not currently available online. Please consult with Special Collections staff to request access to this digital content.
Other Finding Aids
This online finding aid does not include container lists for accessions received prior to September 2017. Please contact specialcollections@smith.edu to request copies of these contents lists.
Documentary films -- United States -- Production and direction; Housekeeping -- History; Housewives -- History; Laundry -- History; Motion pictures -- United States -- Production and direction; Women motion picture producers and directors -- Biography -- Sources; Independent filmmakers -- Biography -- Sources; Adams, Patch, 1945-; Buffalo Rose Productions; correspondence; Electronic mail; Sound recordings; Motion pictures; Videotapes; Audiotapes; Interviews; photographs; DVD video discs; CD-Roms; Notes; Computer media; Web archives; Cantow, Roberta; Cantow, Roberta
- Roberta Cantow's websites, Captured Aug 18, 2017; 2017-S-0057; 4 website (4 archived websites)
  Scope and Contents
  Four archived websites relating to Cantow's film projects,with video clips, trailers, reviews, and additional documentation: "Accordions Rising" (http://www.accordionsrising.com); Bloodtime Moontime Dreamtime Trilogy" (http://www.originaldigital.net/bmd); "Not a Still Life" (http://www.originaldigital.net/notastill-life/); and "Original Digital" (http://www.originaldigital.net), Cantow's film company. The sites were captured in August 2017; none of the sites are currently being added to by Cantow.
  - Accordions Rising website, 1 website
  - Bloodtime Moontime Dreamtime Trilogy website, 1 website
  - Not a Still Life website, 1 website (1 archived website)
  - Original Digital website, 1 website (1 archived website)
- Roberta Cantow papers addition, 1990-2018; 2018-S-0004; 1.25 linear feet (1 legal size full document box, 1 legal size half document box, and one oversize box)
  This series consists of materials added to the collection by Cantow in 2018. It includes correspondence, notes, reviews, marketing, and viewer responses to several of Cantow's recent videos: "Clotheslines," "If This Ain't Heaven," "Bloodtime, Moontime, Dreamtime," "Not a Still Life," "Scapes," and Accordian Rising." Also a small amount of personal correspondence and writings.
  - Correspondence regarding Clotheslines and If This Ain't Heaven, 2018 (Box 1)
  - Proposals, marketing, and correspondence for Bloodtime, Moontime, Dreamtime, 2001-2009 (Box 1)
  - Scapes original proposal, 1990 (Box 1)
  - Accordions Rising promotional materials, comments, ephemera, 2016-2017 (Box 1)
  - Not a Still Life: correspondence, feedback, work in progress, 2011-2013 (Box 1)
  - The Magnificent Leap: notes and video recording, 2017; 1 folders; 1 items (1 DVD) (Box 2)
  - Body Writing Retreat journal, undated (Box 2)
  - Accordions Rising collected ephemera and pre-production, including correspondence, 2010-2017 (Box 2)
  - Original proposal for Accordions Rising, work shop title: Accordions Alive and Kicking, 2014 (Box 2)
  - Reviews of Clotheslines and Birthing the Crone, 2016-2017 (Box 2)
  - Poster for Accordions Rising, 2016 (Box 3)
  - Video recording of Accordions Rising, 2015; 1 items (1 DVD) (Box 3)
  - Audio recording of a radio interview of Roberta Cantow on WIOX, 2016 November 18; 2 items 2 CDs (parts 1 and 2) (Box 3)
  - Video recordings of Not a Still Life, 2013; 2 items (1 Betacam videocassette and 1 DV cam cassette) (Box 3)